DAN KLEIN: Now let's talk about
enforcing arc consistency for an
entire CSP.
Well, this is going to be a simple
form of propagation.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to make sure all of the arcs are
consistent all at once.
And when that's done, we will have
done a more aggressive job than
forward checking of pruning down the
remaining domains, and hopefully saved
ourselves some work.
So the idea is we're always going
to delete from the tail.
Now let's look at this configuration.
Q is green, WA is red, and we know that
NT and SA can't both be blue in
terms of actually getting a solution.
Forward checking left us here.
It looks like everything's OK.
We'll eventually in a backtracking
search discover were wrong, but let's
see if we can figure out an algorithm
which will detect the
failure right away.
Well, in order to enforce arc
consistency, the algorithm's actually
pretty simple.
We're going to visit every single arc,
check if it's consistent, and if not,
we're going to delete
stuff from the tail.
Hopefully, this whole process will
converge and we'll end up with
something that's consistent
everywhere.
So what can we do?
Well, we can look over here.
We can say New South
Wales and Victoria.
We could look at them and say,
is this arc consistent?
Well let's think about it.
We have to check everything in
the trunk, that's Victoria.
Is there any value in the trunk
which guarantees us failure?
Here?
No, because if I pick red in
the trunk, I can pick blue
at New South Wales.
If I pick blue at Victoria, then I
can pick red at New South Wales.
And so there's no problem.
This constraint, it receives
the stamp of consistency.
All right, so this arc is consistent.
Now we can check this arc.
So we look at Southern Australia
and New South Wales.
They're adjacent, s they can't
be the same color.
And so we look.
And Southern Australia, if we assign
blue, will it work out?
Yes.
OK, it's consistent.
So, so far, we haven't
had to do anything.
But let's say we look at the
arc in this direction.
Well now we're looking at New South
Wales and we're asking, are there any
values here at the tail that
will doom us on this arc?
The answer now is, yes, we better not
pick blue because if we do, there's no
way to assign at SA without
violating a constraint.
So, we delete it.
Now, of course, we can continue doing
this for arc after arc after arc.
But the interesting thing is, let's
go back to that arc we just did.
We just declared this arc
here to be consistent.
Is it still consistent?
No, it just stopped being consistent.
And it stopped being consistent
because something
disappeared from its head.
And so when blue went out of its
head, now suddenly red is no
longer OK in the tail.
And so in order to make this
arc consistent again, we
need to do some deleting.
This is basically the algorithm
for enforcing arc consistency.
The important thing to remember is that
we're going to visit all of the
arcs over and over and over again until
everybody is simultaneously
consistent.
Why this is a good idea?
Well, it prunes things down a lot
more than forward checking.
It also can detect failure.
So for example, in the version shown
here, if we check the arc from
Southern Australia to the Northern
Territory, we would delete blue from
Southern Australia and then we would
see an empty domain and we'd fail.
So in fact, it will solve
our original case.
When we check these arcs over and over,
the reason we have to check them
more than once is because whenever a
variable loses a value, all of the
incoming arcs need to be rechecked.
So we're going to have to check
things multiple times.
What's the role of this thing
in the backtracking search?
You make an assignment, you enforce the
consistency of a whole bunch of
arcs, it may take awhile.
Then you make another assignment, and
then you enforce the consistency of a
whole bunch of stuff,
it may take a while.
And you go on recursing.
It makes each step slower, but hopefully
you'll have to do less
backtracking.
And this should remind you
of something from search.
What's this remind you of from search?
This should remind you of A* from
search, where computing the heuristic
cost time, but hopefully reduced the
amount of actual search tree action
you had to do.
All right, so, what's the
algorithm look like?
I'm not going to walk through the
entire pseudocode because we've
already pretty much covered it.
But it's in the slides here for you.
The important bits are there is going to
be a queue, which initially is all
of the arcs in the CSP.
And as long as there's stuff in the
queue, we're going to take something
off the queue, we're going to make that
arc consistent by removing values
from its tail as needed.
If anything was actually removed,
stuff may go back on the queue.
Because any time a variable's domain
shrinks, all of its neighbors pointing
to it have to go back on to the queue.
And then we'd run this until
the queue becomes empty.
So you have some worries, like maybe
we'll just run this forever.
Can this run forever?
This can't run forever, because every
time an arc goes on the queue, it went
on the queue because its
head's domain shrank.
That can only happen so many times.
In particular, for a given arc it
can only happen d many times.
How long does it take to remove
the inconsistent values?
Well you have to check everything in the
head, everything in the tail, and
then do a function call to your
constraint, which, let's say, takes
constant time.
OK, so removing the inconsistent values
is going to cost d squared.
There are n squared arcs
to begin with.
And each one may have to
processed d times.
So this whole thing, if you kind of
calculate it in a naive way, it works
out to be n squared d cubed.
And you can shave off a factor
of d if you're clever.
However, that's polynomial.
We know that CSPs are NP-hard, and that
means that detecting all possible
future problems isn't going to work.
Let's see this algorithm running.
Let's go back to my wonderful
illustration of the five queens
problem and the AI space applet.
Right now, looking at this,
it is in fact consistent.
So I could tell this applet to
make this arc consistent.
And if I did that, what would it do?
It would visit every arc, turning it
from blue, meaning it's on the queue,
to green, meaning it is
guaranteed consistent.
And it'll check each one.
But basically, there's nothing
to do at the beginning.
It's very common, though not always
true, that the initial CSP will
already be arc consistent.
Sometimes it's not.
All right, so now it's arc consistent.
Let me reset that.
What would happen in the
backtracking search?
We'd assign something.
So we go here and would keep,
let's say, just the value 1.
That's equivalent to putting
the queen in the corner.
So now the domain of A shrinks.
Let's run arc consistency here.
So once we shrink the domain of A, we
can enforce arc consistency using the
AC-3 algorithm.
And I'll do a little bit of it manually
here, so I can check this arc
going from A to B. And it
was already consistent.
But the arc and the other direction,
think about B here.
I just put a queen up here.
So B can't be 1 or 2.
And so when I enforce this, some things
will disappear from the domain.
I'm going to do the rest
automatically.
And what you'll see is mostly we go
along making things consistent and
turning them green.
Every now and then we'll delete
some values from a domain.
There'll be a flash of red.
And the flash of red is something that
was once consistent becoming no longer
guaranteed consistent and
going back on the queue.
And this is actually a good effect.
As things go from consistent or
inconsistent, and then we process them
again, and something else goes from
consistent to inconsistent, we're
essentially chasing down
the consequences of our
constraints across the graph.
And now we can see that everything is
consistent and we could then continue
with the backtracking search.
But I won't show all of that.
What about arc consistency when we have
constraints that involve more
than two variables?
At the moment, this algorithm is only
defined as I've given it to you for
binary CSPs, meaning they are at most
two variables per constraint.
There are analogs of this for higher
order constraints and there are
variations of this algorithm.
This one, as it's stated here, will
only work for binary CSPs.